hello hello Tony yes how are you it's
Frankie Freitas I'm good
I'm good doing pretty good thought I
would give you a call and find out some
information about this light meter that
you've put together and you sent an
email to me about that and thank you for
sending that if we were to talk about
that what would be the most important
information you'd want the listeners to
know about
the most important thing I want to
listeners to know is is that it's
available okay uh
uh this is something that that I put
together because I I thought there was a
need for it
apparently there used to be a a meter
that everybody liked
called the science mechanics sm-3 yes I
have that one and
um I think that one is out of print at
this point yeah so I think there is a an
opportunity here
uh to replace that meter with uh you
know a 21st century uh upgraded kind of
version and uh I have been doing
Holograms in my basement for about three
years now and
um I basically started
your book with shoebox holography oh
that's great and I've kind of graduated
from laser diodes to higher powered
helium neon lasers and have a small
table and I've I've experimented with
all of the different kinds of silver
halide film that I can inflates that I
can get a hold of and what turned out to
be your favorite to work with so far
well so far I'd have to say
definitely the most reliable and it's
the highest performing one that I've
found
I I think that probably ultimate can
also be very good but I've had a really
strange problem with ultimate in that I
haven't been able to get any that isn't
like totally fogged well that's
interesting I uh I have gotten several
batches
matches the the folks at ultimate have
been very very uh supportive and trying
to trying to help me out I've had
several batches from France I've had one
batch from Canada
thought maybe it was x-rays but now
we're pretty sure that's not the case
and I've tried everything that I can
think of and so we're still in the midst
of sorting out what's going on there but
I think that ultimate probably can give
the same kind of performance you know uh
based on what I've been able to see
you know aside from the fact that I'm
dealing with this horrendous fogging
problem
um but I I expect that it would be
nearly as good or perhaps even better
than BB as far as noise and contrast and
so forth and I suspect it's much more
sensitive
drawback on BB is that it's it's fairly
uh lower sensor or less sensitive I
guess you'd say yeah
um than most everything else so it
requires a longer exposure or higher
power where are you getting your bb
plates from lately I buy them from
vintech okay oh okay yeah yeah
okay they're super to deal with uh you
can place the web order and and the
stuff shows up and uh
yeah did they say about the Ultima that
they think it might be your processing
regimens well um they provide the
developer oh I see okay
so
um we've tried everything we can
possibly think of
the uh there's a there's still an
outside possibility that it's something
to do with my safe lighting okay and
other than that I mean we've we've
exhaustively eliminated
variable that we can think of so far
which is very strange and I completely
believe that it works in some locations
it doesn't seem to work in Andover I
don't know what yeah it's uh hmm
it sometimes one of those variables
turns out to be the most surprising
element yeah you know it could it
do you use tap water
uh we've tried different kinds of ones
yeah okay okay typically I use bottled
water yeah and I tried an experiment
with uh bottled distilled water which I
would have thought either one of those
would be fine the thing is like all of
my regimen uh has worked okay for many
other kinds of films yeah yeah you know
I've got some old eggs I've got um
slavage
and uh I've tried even I've even gotten
Fuji so you know I've tried a lot of
different kinds of film and most of them
worked the way they yeah
that's interesting
but now you have a light meter that's
right I saw a picture of it it's very
nice with the digital readout what are
the functions on there uh essentially
uh it it gives you four numbers at a
time okay that's as much information as
I could squeeze on the display and the
top two numbers are you're reading in
power for the object beam and the
reference beam okay and uh one of the
bottom numbers is the total of the two
beams so it's just adding the power
together and the other is uh typically a
ratio I see and so you can set it up you
can place the sensor where your film is
and you can card off one beam and and
measure the other
for example you could cut off the
reference beam and measure the object
and punch the button in for that yeah
and then you can card off the object
beam and measure the reference and at
that point it'll give you a display of
the ratio I see yeah so if you're
shooting for a particular ratio that you
like you can you can tune it in that way
and it's all real time and the power
readings have trending on them so that
they have a little plus and minus sign
that comes and goes depending on whether
the reading is going up or going down I
see you have to do the mental math a lot
of people noted that they really liked
the ability of an analog meter with a
needle yeah whether things are going up
or down so I added that function in so
that you can use it for adjusting Optics
uh you can find the the center of the
beam you can just set it up and tune
facial filter for a maximum output which
is basically the optimum setting in most
cases unless there's something funny
with your Optics
and it also can do optical density
oh okay yeah so in that case uh you can
set it up so that it measures the uh
basically the log of the ratio of the
two readings and
you would do for that is you as you put
the sensor in a little plastic bag and
put it face up on the table and you can
develop your film and put it in some
stop bath or fix it or something so that
you can turn the lights on and then you
can basically measure the room light
with nothing over the sensor just the
ambient light and then you put your film
over the sensor and measure the other
reading
and it'll compute that the log of that
ratio and tell you what your optical
density is that's interesting I noticed
a lot of the instructions and the spec
sheets that come with the holographic
films fail to mention anything about
final densities at all
right I was always surprised by that
because I know in in the olden days back
in the day of color separations and
things like that and outputting you know
film from like line of type machines uh
Laser Printers and things that you
always went for a density
always put your film under a
densitometer right yeah interesting I
think some people are you know get uh
into the numerical accuracy of it um
some some film manufacturers I think the
slavage webpage does have a a density
versus exposure okay
but I think there's some experimentation
also you know there's kind of a rule of
thumb that I've observed over the three
years that I've been paying attention
uh that transmission Holograms want to
be around one to two and reflection
Holograms want to be two or better yeah
um
so that's that's useful for that I mean
a lot of people just develop by eye
processing schemes don't account for uh
being able to make a density measurement
before you bleach it yeah yeah
but I think it might still be possible
to do that if you if you had a for
example if you had a light source which
was not in the sensitive area you're
using so if you're using red sensitive
film if you had a green LED as a light
source you could probably still go ahead
and do a density reading on it even
before it's bleached yeah yeah and if
it's not you're reading you get back get
it back into the developer right yeah
and let me ask you this is is the LED
the LCD panel that's on your your light
meter is that backlit yes it is great uh
it has a green backlight to it and
um the the backlight
it consumes a lot of a lot of power from
the battery that's the thing draws
almost no power except for the backlight
yeah and so the thing has an automatic
power down if you don't punch any
buttons for five minutes it shuts itself
off wow and then if you just touch a
button it comes back on again well you
really thought of everything with this
didn't you
I've I've had some experience
um building things that involve a
processor and three buttons uh I've
built a number of of different products
for different markets kind of on my own
and so I have kind of a canned Hardware
approach using some of these microchip
computers that are absolutely phenomenal
there's as much processing power in in
these single chips as there was on the
first computer I learned on which was a
pdpa back in 1968. I think around 1970 I
was on maybe a machine one of them
called wangs yeah had Punch Cards yeah
you punched and punched out a program on
a card you put that in punch card into a
little reader and then you go into the
little terminal and do your work yeah
yeah that was something back in the days
of Punch Cards and paper tape
you go back to quite a way too huh yeah
I do uh I
I can remember first getting interested
in lasers and holography from a uh
probably a Popular Science magazine
article about your panthenics and leaf
when they were when they when they ate
their first uh transmission hologram and
uh then I did some holography in the
early 70s when I was uh in high school
I got some information from Scientific
American article and I made split split
beam transmission holograms on my
basement floor I still have some of them
they're they're pretty amazing that
they've lasted this long yeah and then
the internet is an incredible thing
because every once in a while late at
night I'll get bored with whatever I'm
doing and I'll just type something
random into a search engine in about
three years ago I typed amateur
holography into a search engine and that
that was just the beginning of a brand
new hobby for me yeah I've been going uh
pretty steadily ever since well I really
respect the fact that even though you
did Holograms back in the 70s
when you first came on the program you
said you've been involved for three
years because there's nothing that
drives me nuts as much as folks that did
a couple Holograms you know back in the
70s or 80s for a project or whatever or
maybe they worked on it for a year or
whatever and then for 20 years haven't
done anything and then they get back
into the field and the next thing you
know they're saying they've been
involved with holography for 20 years
yeah that drives me crazy
and that's out there too but the
internet is wonderful you know folks
from all over the world will hear your
interview
I don't know if it'll sell any light
meters but they'll listen to the show
but hopefully speaking of which do you
have a standalone website that has
information about this meter because I
can include that link I haven't gotten
that sophisticated yet
um I posted it on the holography Forum
and if folks are interested in getting a
look at it and reading about it I would
direct them there just go to the
holography Forum and look at the for
sale Section
there's a a new product announcement in
there okay and um you know holography is
basically a hobby to me
and thought that I could make a
contribution
to holography by making this meter yeah
this isn't going to be anything that's
going to support me in my old age I know
I know I'm not going to quit my day job
and at the same time if if I'm going to
build a quality product and and I'm not
going to make a kit I'm not going to
make it something that it won't work
yeah stay away from the kits
um really I need to charge a fair price
for it yeah
that's where it's priced and that's
where it's intended to be and what is
the price uh 179.95 US dollars
okay that includes uh a sensor and I use
a a solar cell for a sensor and
um I've chosen that sensor because I've
found that it's inexpensive uh it's a
nice large area so that you can
integrate over an area of the uh of the
plate
uh it's very thin so you can position it
uh in the plane of the of the film
readily you know it's not bulky
um and it also it has a very low
reflectivity
uh yeah yeah it's a very dull surface
which means you don't have to concern
yourself about uh the several percent
that might be reflecting off the front
say from a typical sensor that has a a
glossy shiny face to yeah and that
actually happens when you put a
holographic plate into the plate holder
as well you're still losing a certain
percentage off of that first surface
that you didn't capture when you were
doing the Light reading right yeah
the the meter can be calibrated for
different wavelengths and also for
different sensors if someone has an
application
um for a different type of sensor or a
different wavelength uh than a
calibration I can just come up with a
calibration for it and put it in and uh
it's all reprogrammable so if I come up
with a new idea or new feature or if
someone buys a meter and then later on
wants to you know they go from red to
Green
[Music]
hopefully it'll get better you know as
people come up with new ideas and things
that I can do with it okay so basically
it is for whether you're either using
the meter in the red part of the
spectrum or the green part of the
spectrum right out of the box right yeah
and and the power range
um well the power range is somewhat
affected by the sensor and the power
range that I'm able to really feel
confident with is up to about 35
milliwatts okay
that's the most powerful laser I have
here
electrically speaking it reads from uh
one microwatt to one watt
but you know obviously when you get into
the higher power levels you may have to
do some calibrating here with a sensor
I'd get one myself but I I work by eye
now like the old photographers would do
back in the early days of photography I
I rarely even do uh readings anymore
myself
I think after you you make so many
holograms for so many years you can
pretty much just look at a setup and
you're already in the ballpark your mind
already knows where you need to be but
right but for someone that's just
starting out it's it's of utmost
importance
because you're training your mind at
that point that's right to
take a look at something get a reading
from it and the mind remembers over time
it may not remember just after doing it
for a week but if you're doing it you're
doing it day after day week after week
and year after year eventually you just
look at something and you can pretty
much tell where you're going to be with
it I agree with that and and I think one
thing that makes that whole process
easier is if you can standardize
so for example
um I just I just do red and I stay with
a 4x5 inch format and my table
geometries are very good stable
um they're usually one of two choices
depending on whether I'm making H1s or
H2 copies and
um
with all of that you're right you you do
develop a feeling or an intuition for uh
what what works
but still if if you're experimenting or
you're going a little bit outside your
envelope maybe with a different color or
different laser or sometimes the subject
matter too can be a little yes or a
different film like
I mean most of the silver films are are
fairly similar but there is some
variation I definitely think the
ultimate's more sensitive and the BB is
less sensitive and if using a brand new
film you probably want to start where
the manufacturer
recommends yes it's a good starting
point and a meter can help you make sure
you're starting there and help you
eliminate some of the variables right
out of the box yeah yeah
have you worked on any larger format
films or plates yet like eight by ten
and up no I haven't no as I said I've
kind of specialized
table that I've built it's a hexcan
table oh okay so it's literally soda
cans uh between two skins of Steel that
was John clayer that started that yeah
it might have been him yeah but there
were a lot of different people who who
investigated it and uh you know I built
one another interesting thing about my
Approach is that
I don't have a lot of room even though I
have a reasonably sized house I have a
lot of other Hobbies going on I'm into
amateur radio oh okay model rocketry and
and so space is a premium and I I didn't
have a room that I could dedicate as a
dark room so I've taken over uh actually
my wife ended up convincing me to
remodel the downstairs bathroom so that
can be used both for chemistry and for
regular downstairs bathroom functions
you've been bitten by the bug so
um one of the things that I developed is
a technique where most of my my uh
processes can
carried out in room line
so I use
um 5x7 graphlex film holders as my film
holder okay and I rebuild them so that
you can put a piece of 4x5 film or a
sandwich between glass or you can put a
glass plate in them and they'll it'll be
mounted stably
a trick in itself and then you can put
the slides on this thing and you can
carry it around the house wow and then
my table is enclosed uh in the phone
core it's about a three foot Cube around
this two foot table
and on one side there's a port where
I've cut out a square and I made what
looks like a graphics camera entry okay
it's uh insulated from light and
vibration by several layers of black
trash bag plastic and you can position
everything you want inside the box and
put the plate holder in and close up the
box and then pull the dark slides out
and then you can make an exposure that
way do you have any pictures anywhere of
this because this is sounding awful
familiar to me like I've seen some
pictures of of your studio or something
I think I've put some pictures like this
uh up on
yeah because it all sounds very familiar
like I've seen it so I may have
described some of it and put up some
pictures yeah because I've never been
there
we've never met right no no we've never
met no all right anything you want to
add Tony we're coming up well actually
over 20 minutes now I like to keep it
short just so the file sizes don't get
too big because the audio files some
people are still on dial-up modems and
that's fine but what I try to do is to
make everybody happy so I try to keep
the file sizes as small as possible
because they're downloading on you know
dial-up modems and things still
anything you'd like to add before we
close it out
uh I think we've I'm just uh kind of
looking at a cheat sheet here to see if
we've covered everything um
uh basically it's a it's an accurate
light meter
um it gives you some computations that
help you out it has real-time readings
uh that you can use if you're making
adjustments or if you're trying to set
beam ratios
and runs on a battery
and simple to use
and uh an affordable and affordable yes
so I'm I'm hoping that some some folks
will be interested in it and uh you know
I I'm just trying to
whatever kind of a contribution I can to
the Hobby yeah
and really that's my point of view on it
I I'm not like many people who sort of
think that holography is going to be the
next big thing well good for you because
you're in for a big surprise
for many many years yeah no I'm drawing
a blank so just hold on with me here for
a second
um how can someone get in touch with you
um do you want to give your phone number
do you want me to put your phone number
on the on the holotalk website uh page
when people listen to the show or what
do you want them to do probably the best
would be to um
give out
detail address okay I think that and
I'll place a link to that also so that
people can just click on that and send
you an email yeah yeah that would be
that would be the best thing do you have
a PayPal account where people can pay
you online or you just check the money
order thing uh I do have a PayPal
account okay at the moment I can only
accept uh uh payment from a checking
account I can't okay
payment from a credit card all right
I'm just really a user I'm not a seller
I see well you can let everybody you can
work that out with everyone else when
they contact you I can't take credit
cards I can't accept credit cards oh
okay um
access to a merchant account
okay so I want to give them the email
address
sure uh it's
v-a-r-o-c-k-t-e-e-r at a
at.com okay
oh okay and that's from one of my other
hobbies that I resurrected by typing
something into the internet late at
night
hmm
yeah I did some little model rocketing
when I was a kid
it was a lot of fun wow Like
hologography the Model rocketry area has
grown up as well
when you were a kid you probably thought
a c or a d was a big engine yeah and
nowadays uh the the model rocketry
and go as high as M wow and each letter
is a doubling it's a doubling of the
amount of power isn't that something I
know some people launch cameras and
everything on now cameras video
um
small children
[Laughter]
isn't that something huh
well I'll have to look no I'm not going
to look that up I'm not going to look
that up that's it I've got too many
things going on now that's right when I
turned 50 I chose there were a few
things that I was going to continue to
do and I was dropping everything else
and I chose holography getting back
involved with music and composing again
which I've started to do I put a
recording studio in and fitness you know
cycling I'm just boxing and things of
that nature that I've been doing for
years well that's a great one that's it
that is it nothing else and nothing new
this is going to take me out for the
rest of my life and I don't I'm not
going to put model rocketry into a
search engine
that was a lot of fun though I have seen
some videos of people who have had the
small
USB type cameras or whatever it was that
they had on the nose of the rocket and
they'd launch that up into the
neighborhoods and stuff and it was like
I've got to do this
but I'm gonna stay away from it all
right Tony
it was really nice talking to you
well thank you very much for calling I
hope we get a chance to meet sometime
yeah we're not too far apart from one
another no and uh maybe one of these
days they'll they'll have some kind of a
get-together uh in the Northeast I know
that they they've been trying to have
one I tried to have one in Georgia but
it kind of fizzled out yeah
they had one in the Northeast I think we
would we would get together yeah
well I get up there sometimes around
Cape Cod
Martha's Vineyard area I don't know how
far that is
from where you are
well um but if I ever find myself coming
up there again probably won't be this
summer
I'm only about a two-hour drive from the
cape okay
you know about an hour and a half from
the bridges Infamous Bridges I usually
stay in a town called Falmouth yeah I
don't know where that is yeah yeah so
that's only about an hour and a half for
me yeah then we take the boat over
all right Tony all right have a good
rest of the night and uh
at some point I'll get this all I don't
think we need to do too much I don't do
too much editing on it if I Stumble over
something I usually leave it in but if
someone else stumbles I take it out for
them if they want to but you did a
wonderful job you were prepared you knew
what you wanted to say and you got it
across comprehensively and I think we'd
be ready to go with it great thank you
very much for the opportunity sure adios
Amigo all right thanks Frank talk to you
later bye